

# Alexandre Chapiro

I am interested in applied perception and psychophysics as related to computational display, as well as image and video processing techniques. In particular, I've worked on topics in stereo 3D, high dynamic range, brightness and color, frame rate and motion, user experience and virtual reality.

## Professional Experience

2020-now Facebook Reality Labs

Senior Conduct research and explore topics on applied perception, with special focus on

Researcher immersive displays

affiliation Applied Perception Science Team, managed by Kevin MacKenzie

2018-2020 Apple Inc., Cupertino

Senior Display Helped identify and cultivate new display and image processing technologies and

Engineer experiences for future Apple products

affiliation Core Display Incubation Team, managed by Nicolas Bonnier

2017-2018 Dolby Laboratories, Sunnyvale

Senior Conducted research and obtained experimental results on human perception factors

Researcher relevant to business needs

affiliation Applied Vision Science group, managed by Robin Atkins

2011-2016 **Disney Research, Zurich** 

Researcher Conducted research on novel displays, stereo 3D, high dynamic range, high framerate

and human perception resulting in four patent applications and several publications

affiliation Stereo and Displays group, managed by Aljoša Smolić

#### Education

2011-2015 PhD in Computer Science

institution Federal Institute of Technology Zurich (ETHZ), Zurich, Switzerland

thesis title Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays

affiliation Computer Graphics Laboratory

supervisors Prof. Markus Gross. Co-Advisor: Dr. Aljoša Smolić

	Masters' Degree in Applied Mathematics Institute of Pure and Applied Mathematics (IMPA), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
	Improving Mobile Video
affiliation	Visgraf laboratory
supervisors	Prof. Paulo Cezar Pinto Carvalho. Co-Advisor: Prof. Luiz Velho
2007-2009	Undergraduate Degree in Mathematics
institution	Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF), Juiz de Fora, Brazil
thesis title	An Introduction to Degree Theory
affiliation	Computer Graphics Laboratory
supervisors	Prof. Luiz Faria, Marcelo Bernardes Vieira
2016-2016	Dolby Laboratories, Sunnyvale
Intern	Conducted research on the human visual system guided by business unit needs
affiliation	Applied Vision Science group, managed by Robin Atkins
	Teaching
	<b>Teaching assistant</b> , <i>Math. Foundations of Computer Graphics and Vision</i> , ETHZ. Graduate class teaching mathematical techniques in visual computing
Feb.2015 to Jun.2015	<b>Teaching assistant</b> , <i>Math. Foundations of Computer Graphics and Vision</i> , ETHZ.
	<b>Teaching assistant</b> , <i>Informatik 1</i> , ETHZ. Undergradute class teaching fundaments of informatics to engineering students
Feb.2013	<b>Teaching assistant</b> , <i>Informatik 1</i> , ETHZ.

#### Academic Honors

to Jun.2013

- 2015 Second youngest PhD to graduate from the CS department at ETH Zurich at 25
- 2011 Finished 2-year Master's program at the National Institute of Pure and Applied Mathematics in 18 months
- 2009 Finished 4-year undergraduate program in Mathematics at the Federal University of Juiz de Fora in 3 years with the highest GPA in the graduating class
- 2007 Ranked 1st in admission examinations, Federal University of Juiz de Fora
- 2006 Gold Medalist, Brazilian Astronomy Olympiad
- 2006 Gold Medalist, Brazilian Mathematics Olympiad for Public School Students. 95th place among approximately 5.3 million students
- 2005 Gold Medalist, Brazilian Mathematics Olympiad for Public School Students. 9th place among approximately 3.8 million students

## Academic Service

Commitee 2021, SIBGRAPI Journal Track International Program Committee.

2019, SIBGRAPI Journal Track International Program Committee.

2018, SIBGRAPI International Program Committee.

Reviewing 2020, Eurographics, IEEE TIP.

2019, SIGGRAPH, Eurographics, IEEE TIP.

2018, SIBGRAPI, Eurographics.

2017, SIGGRAPH, Pacific Graphics, IEEE TIP.

2016, SIGGRAPH Asia, Graphics Interface, IEEE TIP, JOSA.

2015, SIGGRAPH, SIGGRAPH Asia, ICIP, IEEE CG&A, IEEE TVCG.

**2014**, Pacific Graphics, CG Forum.

2012, 3DV.

## Awards and Funding

Oct.2011 Participant, European Commission Program FP7.

to Oct.2013

Mar.2010 Awarded, Master program fellowship, CNPq.

to Jul.2011

Jan.2009 Awarded, Undergraduate research scholarship, FAPEMIG.

to Dec.2009

Jan.2008 Awarded, Undergraduate research scholarship, CNPq.

to Dec.2008

Mar.2007 Awarded, Scholarship for winners OBMEP 2006 mathematics olympics, CNPq.

to Jan.2008

Mar.2006 Awarded, Scholarship for winners OBMEP 2005 mathematics olympics, CNPq.

to Jan.2007

Jan.2005 Awarded, High-school research scholarship, CNPq.

to Dec.2005

 Obs.: CNPq is the Brazilian national funding agency. FAPEMIG is the funding agency for the state of Minas Gerais, Brazil

## Invited Talks and Presentations

invited talk: Echoes of SIGGRAPH'20.

IMPA 2020, Brazil, hosted by Luiz Velho

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

TU Delft 2019, Netherlands, hosted by Elmar Eisemann

invited talk: Cinematic Motion.

NAB show 2018, Las Vegas, invited by Jaclyn Pytlarz

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

IBM 2017, Rio de Janeiro, hosted by Emilio Vital Brazil

invited talk: **Computer Graphics**, (popular lecture).

IF Sudeste MG 2017, Juiz de Fora, hosted by Elena Konstantinova

invited talk: **Computer Graphics**, (popular lecture).

IF Sudeste MG 2016, Rio Pomba, hosted by Lucas Lattari

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

Dolby Laboratories 2016, Sunnyvale, hosted by Timo Kunkel

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

Technicolor 2015, Rennes, hosted by Erik Reinhard

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for 3D Displays.

Max Planck Institut 2015, Saarbrucken, hosted by Piotr Didyk

paper talk: Stereo from Shading.

**EGSR 2015** 

paper talk: Perceptual Evaluation of Cardboarding in 3D Content Visualization.

SAP 2015

paper talk: Optimizing Stereo-to-Multiview Conv. for Autostereo. Displays.

Eurographics 2015

## Languages

Portuguese Fluent Native speaker

Russian Fluent Native speaker

English Fluent TOEFL iBT 117/120, Cambridge FCE and CAE exams with A grades

Spanish Fluent 3 years of school in Spain

French Advanced Alliance Française DELF diplome - 2005

German Beginner Approximately A2 level

## Publications

## **Papers**

## FovVideoVDP: A visible difference predictor for wide field-of-view video,

SIGGRAPH, 2021,

Mantiuk, Denes, Chapiro, Kaplanyan, Rufo, Bachy, Lian, Patney

## A Luminance-Aware Model of Judder Perception,

ACM Transactions on Graphics (TOG) , 2019 (presented at SIGGRAPH'20),  $\underline{\text{Chapiro}},$  Atkins, Daly

## Influence of Screen Size and Field of View on Perceived Brightness,

ACM Transactions on Applied Perception (TAP) , 2018, Chapiro, Kunkel, Atkins, Daly

## Unfolding the 8-bit Era,

European Conference on Visual Media Production 2015, Zund, Berard, Chapiro, Schmid, Ryffel, Bermano, Gross, Sumner

## Art-Directable Continuous Dynamic Range Video,

Compters & Graphics, Elsevier, 2015, Chapiro, Aydin, Stefanoski, Croci, Smolic, Gross

#### Video Content and Structure Description Based on Keyframes, Clusters and Storyboards,

IEEE International Workshop on Multimedia Signal Processing, Xiamen-China, 2015, Junyent, Beltran, Farre, Pont-Tuset, Chapiro, Smolic

#### Stereo from Shading,

Eurographics Symposium on Rendering, Darmstadt-Germany, 2015. (E&I track), Chapiro, O'Sullivan, Jarosz, Gross, Smolic

## Perceptual Evaluation of Cardboarding in 3D Content Visualization,

ACM Symposium on Applied Perception, Vancouver-Canada, 2014. (Short paper), Chapiro, Diamanti, Poulakos, O'Sullivan, Smolic, Gross

## Optimizing Stereo-to-Multiview Conversion for Autostereoscopic Displays,

Eurographics, Strasbourg-France, 2014, Chapiro, Heinzle, Aydin, Poulakos, Zwicker, Smolic, Gross

#### Towards Mobile HDR Video,

Eurographics, Llandudno-UK, 2011. (Extended abstract) Castro, Chapiro, Cicconet, Velho

## Detection of High Frequency Regions in Multiresolution,

International Conference on Image Processing, Cairo-Egypt, 2009. Mota, Perez, Castro, Chapiro, Vieira

#### High Frequency Assessment from Multiresolution Analysis,

International Conference on Computational Science, Baton Rouge-USA, 2009 Castro, Perez, Mota, Chapiro, Vieira, Freire

## Patents

#### Frame rate conversion metadata,

US Patent US11019302 B2, 2020 Pytlarz, Atkins, Pieri, Chapiro, Daly

#### Luminance adaption to minimize discomfort and improve visibility,

US Patent US 20200202814 A1, 2020 Chapiro, Atkins, Daly

#### Virtual reality cinema-immersive movie watching for headmounted displays,

US Patent US10769754 B2, 2020 Chapiro, Atluru, Chun, Haricharan, Rozzi, Ruggieri, Ninan

## Systems and methods for automatic key frame extraction and storyboard interface generation for video,

US Patent US9552520 B1, 2017 (Related to our 2015 paper) Smolic, Martin, Pont-Tuset, Chapiro, Guiu

## Methods for creating and distributing art-directable continuous dynamic range video,

US20160353164 A1, 2016 (Related to our 2015 paper) Smolic, Chapiro, Croci, Aydin, Stefanoski, Gross

## Visual salience of online video as a predictor of success,

US20170061235 A1, 2015 (Related to our 2015 poster) Frey, Accardo, Sumner, Huber, Chapiro

## Depth modification for display applications,

US20150348273 A1, 2015 (Related to our 2014 paper) Chapiro, Aydin, Poulakos, Heinzle, Smolic

Three additional patents currently in review

#### **Book Chapters**

#### Discrete Wavelets on Edges,

InTech open publisher, 2011 Chapiro , Knop, Mota, Perez, Bernardes, Freire

#### **Posters**

## The Influence of Visual Salience on Video Consumption Behavior A Survival Analysis Approach,

ACM Web Science, Oxford-United Kingdom, 2015 Huber, Scheibehenne, Chapiro, Frey, Sumner

#### Filter Based Deghosting for Exposure Fusion Video,

SIGGRAPH, Vancouver-Canada, 2011. Student Research Competition Semi-Finalist Chapiro, Cicconet, Velho

#### Towards Mobile HDR Video,

International Conference on Computational Photography, Pittsburg-USA, 2011 Castro, Chapiro, Cicconet, Velho

#### Mountain's Pass Theorem.

Minas-Gerais Meeting of Partial Diferential Equations, Itajuba-Brazil, 2009 Chapiro, Pereira

#### Other

**L** +1 (650) 770 6470 • ☑ alex@chapiro.net • **Q** chapiro.net **in** alexandre-chapiro-a8342520

## Image Domain Warping for Advanced 3D Video Applications,

IEEE COMSOC MMTC E - Letter, 2014. (Invited letter)

Smolic, Wang, Lang, Stefanoski, Farre, Greisen, Heinzle, Schaffner, Chapiro, Sorkine-Hornung, Gross

## Computational Photography,

IMPA, Rio de Janeiro-Brazil, 2011. (Technical report) Castro, Chapiro, Velho